Guide to the Henry W. Jones papers, 1813-1877 RL.11543
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Henry W. Jones papers
1813-1877
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jones, Henry W., d. approximately 1871.
RL.11543
4 Linear Feet
Henry W. Jones was a farmer, lawyer, magistrate, and distiller from Granville County, North Carolina.
Biographical / Historical
Henry William Jones was born about 1792 in Granville County, North Carolina. He enlisted in the Army in 1812, but did not see battle. Following the war, he married Sarah Parker and they had several children together. During the course of his life, Jones served as a magistrate, a farmer, and a distiller in Granville County.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Henry W. Jones papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase and gift in 1984.
Collection Overview
Correspondence and Assorted Family Material is primarily personal correspondence sorted by year. One folder contains handwritten genealogical information about Jones and his lineage. Almost all of the correspondence is addressed to Henry W. Jones, though most of the correspondence came after his death in late 1871 or early 1872, and is addressed to a son, Edward H. Jones of Oxford, N.C. Nearly all of the correspondents, both before and after 1871/1872, were children and children-in-law of Henry W. Jones, most of whom resided in Hopkins Co., Ky. The notable exceptions to this are John and Alice Beasley, a son-in-law and daughter who lived in Tex., and P. H. Gooch, a nephew who lived in Farmington, Mo. Agriculture and family matters are the dominant subjects covered by the correspondence. One family matter of particular interest was an effort by some of Henry W. Jones's children, particularly Soloman W. Jones, a local Methodist preacher, to convert their father to Christianity. These same letters also document the revivals that swept Kentucky in the 1850s. There are also several letters that comment on life in the C.S.A. Army, including ones by E. H. Jones (55th Regiment, N.C. Troops) and B. F. Jones (17th Regiment, N.C. Troops).
The first portion of Legal and Financial Papers contains individual folders with records relating to Jones's career as a magistrate (tax records, election rolls, and warrants) as well personal financial information (distillery taxes and personal tax receipts). The remainder of the series is general financial and legal correspondence sorted by year. This series also contains several account books for business partnerships between Jones and his father-in-law, David Parker.
The final series--Printed materials, clippings, and printed work--contains newspaper clippings, political pamphlets, and other printed material related to farming, legal issues, as well as North Carolina and national politics.
Elections -- North Carolina; Slaves -- North Carolina; Tax collection -- United States -- History; Granville County (N.C.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Revivals -- Kentucky; Distilleries -- North Carolina; Jones, Edward H.; Beasley, John; Beasley, Alice; Confederate States of America. Army -- Military life; Confederate States of America. Army. North Carolina Infantry Regiment, 55th; Confederate States of America. Army. North Carolina Infantry Regiment, 17th
- Correspondence and Assorted Family Papers, 1828-1877
  - Genealogical Notes, undated (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Handwritten notes on the children and spouses of Henry W. Jones and some notes on his ancestry.
  - Correspondence, 1828-1871; 31 folders (Box 1)
    Personal and family correspondence, organized by year.
  - Correspondence, 1872-1877 and undated; 6 folders (Box 2)
    Personal and family correspondence sorted by year; includes undated material.
- Legal and Financial Papers, 1813-1870
  Series contains tax receipts, warrants, election results, documents related to the purchase and sale of enslaved people, pages from account books, and general business and financial-related correspondence.
  - Tax Rolls, 1834-1845 (Box 2)
    Partial property tax rolls
  - Purchase and Sale of Enslaved People, 1814-1859 (Box 2)
    Receipts, bills of sale, and other materials related to the purchase and sale of enslaved people.
  - Election Results, 1838-1852 (Box 2)
    Incomplete election tallies and results from Eastern North Carolina localities
  - Warrants, 1823-1857 (Box 2)
    Signed and notarized warrants, writs of habeus corpus, and other legal affidavits.
  - Tax Receipts, 1823-1868 (Box 2)
    Receipts for taxes paid, includes property taxes, poor tax, and work taxes.
  - Distillery, 1863-1867 (Box 2)
    Tax receipts and other legal documents related to distillery operation
  - Account book pages, 1815-1830 (Box 2)
    Pages from account book covering purchases from December 1815 to August 1830
  - Account book pages, 1845-1849 (Box 2)
    Account book pages, entries crossed out
  - Account book pages, 1850-1860 (Box 2)
    Account book pages, entries crossed out.
  - Account book pages, 1814-1816 (Box 2)
    Partial account ledger tracking purchases and sales from February 1814 to October 1816
  - General financial material, 1813-1830; 11 folders (Box 2)
    General financial records including correspondence, receipts, invoices, and orders.
  - General financial material, 1831-1850; 20 folders (Box 3)
  - General financial material, 1851-1870; 21 folders (Box 4)
  - General financial material, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Purchase list, 1856 (Oversize-folder 2)
    List of items purchased
  - Tax lists, 1849, 1854 (Oversize-folder 1)
- Printed Materials, Clippings, and Published Works, 1830-1859
  Printed material, newspaper clippings, posters, printed and published material, and ephemera
  - Printed material, undated (Box 4)
    Printed material including pamphlets, government documents, advertisements, militia documents, and photocopies of North Carolina State Bonds (transfered to Bond Collection)
  - Directions for making whiskey, undated (Box 4)
    Handwritten recipe for whiskey including measurements, materials, and directions
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 4)
    Newspaper clippings without date or paper information
  - Memorandum book, 1859 (Box 4)
    Memo book with notes in pencil
  - Miscellaneous material, undated (Box 4)
    Other hand-written material, including political tracts, directions for mixing materials, and other miscellaneous papers
  - Ephemera, undated (Box 4)
    Leather datebook, cigarette rolling papers, and scraps of other material
  - Posters and large newspaper clippings, 1842-1858 and undated (Oversize-folder 2)
    Newspaper clippings from 1842 election, poster, and advertisement.
  - School form (blank) and oversize newspaper clippings with legislature coverage, 1826-1865 and undated (Oversize-folder 1)